Guide to the Willard Dickerman Straight papers, 1825-1925.
Straight, Willard Dickerman papers, 1825-1925.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Willard Dickerman Straight papers, 1825-1925.
1260
Willard Dickerman, Straight 1880-1918.
28.6 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, reports, diaries, manuscripts,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Microfilmed papers of Willard D. Straight consist of personal and official correspondence, both original and typescript copies, and reports chiefly concerning his association with the Chinese Imperial Customs Service (1902-04). Documented is his employment with Reuters during the Russo-Japanese War (1904-05); with the United States Department of State in Korea and Manchuria (1904-09); and with Edward H. Harriman, Jacob H. Schiff, and J.P. Morgan and Company (1904-09).
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Willard D. Straight was born on January 31, 1880 in Oswego, New York. His father died in 1886; the next year Straight and his family moved to Japan. In 1890 his mother died and he returned to Oswego. He attended Bordentown Military Institute in New Jersey, 1896-97, and majored in architecture at Cornell University, 1897-1901.
In November 1901 he was appointed to a position with the Chinese Imperial Maritime Customs Service, and from 1902-04 he was personal secretary to Sir Robert Hart, Inspector General of the Service in Peking. Also in 1902, he illustrated VERSE AND WORSE for J.O.P. Bland. In June 1905 he was appointed Vice-Consul under Edwin V. Morgan in Seoul, Korea.
In June 1906 he was appointed Consul-General at Mukden, Manchuria. In 1909 he illustrated HOUSEBOAT DAYS IN CHINA, again for Bland. That June he left the consular service to represent J.P. Morgan and Company and other banks and investors, the American Group.
In 1911, he married Dorothy Payne Whitney. They left China in 1912 when revolution broke out, returning to the United States. Straight continued to encourage investment in China through the American Asiatic Association, of which he became president in 1913. In 1914, the Straights began publication of THE NEW REPUBLIC.
In 1915 Straight resigned from J.P. Morgan and was appointed third vice president of American International Corporation. He enlisted in the U.S. Army in 1917. In 1918, while arranging for the arrival of the American Peace Mission in Paris, Straight contracted pneumonia, and he died on December 1, 1918.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Microfilmed papers of Willard D. Straight consist of personal and official correspondence, both original and typescript copies, and reports chiefly concerning his association with the Chinese Imperial Customs Service (1902-04). Documented is his employment with Reuters during the Russo-Japanese War (1904-05); with the United States Department of State in Korea and Manchuria (1904-09); and with Edward H. Harriman, Jacob H. Schiff, and J.P. Morgan and Company (1904-09).
Letters and reports address in particular the interest of Theodore Roosevelt and William Howard Taft in the Harriman-Schiff-Morgan proposals for investments in China from 1907-09; and concern Japanese diplomacy and finance, 1909-10; Straight's interest in THE NEW REPUBLIC and the American Asiatic Association; his role in the "preparedness" campaign in New York through the Mayor's Committee on National Defense (1915-17); his connection with the American International Corporation (1916-18)
his conduct of joint purchasing operations for the French and British governments through J.P. Morgan (1915-16); his efforts to establish the merit system in the State Department career service; and his administration of the War Risk Insurance Bureau and the establishment of its headquarters overseas (1918). In addition, there are many letters to his wife, with comments on the Red Cross, U.S. Army promotional policies, Pershing as a commander, and the American Expeditionary Force.
The collection also includes his diaries (1901-18), with transcriptions, reports, and other papers about the development of railroads, waterways, and coal mines in China and Manchuria, currency reform in China, the proposed international loan to China (1909-11), and the Far Eastern situation in general. There are also books of clippings on the Russo-Japanese War and other events in the Orient, and on the World War I work of Mr. and Mrs. Straight.
Also many letters of condolence, memorials and memoirs written at the time of Straight's death, and correspondence and reports about the building of Willard Straight Hall at Cornell (1919-22).
Non-microfilmed papers include documents on his parents and genealogy; Bordentown Military Institute; military training; Cornell; George Collingwood Bennett, Straight's valet, including photographs and memorabilia; tributes, publications, drafts, inventories and seances following Straight's death; correspondence; and a diary.
Also included are photographs and photograph albums, postcards, and commercial views; published and unpublished watercolors; pen, pencil, and crayon sketches; and charcoals by Willard Straight. This includes student work such as architectural drawings, watercolors, life drawings, and sketches for the CORNELLIAN and the WIDOW, two Cornell newspapers. Also, artwork collected by the Straights, certificates, and maps; and a brass Chinese lock.
Also one leather notebook embossed in gold letters: "Major W. D. Straight."
Article from the Toronto Sunday World, Oct. 13, 1912, "How I escaped the Chinese bandits", chronicling Dorothy Whitney's escape from looters at the Pierpont Morgan compound in Peking during a recent uprising.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Straight, Willard Dickerman,1880-1918.; Bennett, George Collingwood.; Bland, John Otway Percy, 1863-1945.; Bland, John Otway Percy, 1863-1945.; Elmhirst, Dorothy Payne Whitney Straight.; Harriman, Edward Henry, 1848-1909.; Hart, Robert, 1835-1911; Morgan, Edwin V.; Morgan, J. Pierpont (John Pierpont), 1837-1913.; Pershing, John J. (John Joseph), 1860-1948.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Schiff, Jacob H. (Jacob Henry), 1847-1920.; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; American Asiatic Association.; American Group.; American International Corporation.; Bordentown Military Institute.; China.Imperial Maritime Customs Service.; Cornell University--Buildings.; Cornell University--Periodicals.; Cornell University.; J.P. Morgan & Co.; New York (N.Y.). Mayor's Committee on National Defense.; Red Cross.; Reuters ltd.; United States.Dept. of State.; United States.Bureau of War Risk Insurance.; United States.Army.; Willard Straight Hall (Ithaca, N.Y.)
Titles:
Cornellian.; New Republic.; Widow.
Subjects:
Diplomatic and consular service.; International finance.; International relations.; Military education.; Russo-Japanese War, 1904-1905.; World War, 1914-1918.; Artists, American.; Illustrators; Diplomats
Places:
China.; Japan.; Korea.; Manchuria (China).
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Not all the material in the collection is covered by this guide.
A portion of this collection has been microfilmed. The microfilm (rolls 1-12) for the collection has been digitized and can be viewed here: http://ecommons.cornell.edu/handle/1813/22047.
CONTAINER LIST
- Microfilm Guide
  - Link to a copy of the published finding aid. (5MB PDF)
    The microfilm (rolls 1-12) for the collection has been digitized and can be viewed here: http://ecommons.cornell.edu/handle/1813/22047.
    Digitized microfilm (rolls 1-12) also located on DVD-740-743
- Visual Material
  - Link to a copy of the visual material finding aid and photograph index. Includes artwork, maps, certificates, textiles, photographs, and also some additional collection information.
- Partial Box List
  - Series I Family and Childhood
    - Documents concerning his parents and genealogy.
      - Family Documents and Manuscripts (Box 19, Folder 1)
        Includes biographies of Willard Straight, his parents, Henry H. and Emma Dickerman Straight; Willard Straight's war record, writings of Henry H. Straight, obituary of Emma D. Straight, and school reports of Willard A. Dickerman.
      - Genealogy (Box 19, Folder 2)
        Includes letter describing Straight family as well as a notebook ad letters describing the Needham-Crombie genealogy.
      - Historical Sketches Relating to the First Quarter Century of the State Normal and Training School at Oswego, NY, 1888 (Box 19, Folder 3)
        Includes remarks on Henry H. Straight, Emma D. Straight, and friend Margaret W. Morley, 1888.
      - Sketchbook and sketches--copybook of Emma D. Straight. (Box 19, Folder 4)
      - Scrapbook on Louis Agassiz--assembled by Henry H. Straight. (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence
      - Family Correspondence (Box 19, Folder 5)
        Includes letters among family members and from Willard Straight to family members and others concerning family matters.
      - Diary of Willard Straight, 1890 (Box 31, Folder 9)
      - Scrapbook--greeting cards, c., 1900 (Box 30, Folder 5)
      - Stamp Album--partially filled by Willard Straight. (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Series II Education
    - Bordentown Military Institute, 1896-1897
      - Bordentown--printed views of campus, grade reports, and measurements of Willard Straight. (Box 19, Folder 6)
      - "The Skirmisher", 189,618,971,900 (Box 19, Folder 7)
        Magazine of Bordentown Military Institute for 1896, 1897, 1900; includes articles by Willard Straight.
      - Notebook--"Tabulations in Rhetoric" (Box 30, Folder 1)
        Includes notes, sketches, writings about Alpha Omega society at Bordentown.
    - Cornell University, 1897-1901
      - Memorabilia--student handbook and dance card for 1899 Easter party., 1899 (Box 19, Folder 8)
      - Publications--includes copy of Cornell Era, and Willard Straight's drawings for publication. (Box 19, Folder 9)
      - The Widow, 1901 (Box 19, Folder 10)
      - Grade Reports and Class Notes, 1900 (Box 19, Folder 11)
        Notes of History of Art with Olaf Brauner; grade reports from Cornell and Oswego High School.
      - The Annual of the College of Architecture, 1897-1898, 1891-1898 (Box 19, Folder 12)
        Includes copies of Willard Straight's drawings.
      - The Annual of the College of Architecture, 1898-1899., 1898-1899 (Box 19, Folder 13)
      - A Book of Designs sn Drawings, College of Architecture, 1901, annotated., 1901 (Box 19, Folder 14)
      - Letters--to "Miss Drew," n.d. (Box 19, Folder 15)
      - Details of Building Construction--includes typed notes. (Box 31, Folder 3)
      - Scrapbook, 1897-1901 (Box 32, Folder 1)
        Describes Willard Straight's activities at Cornell and includes photos of classmates, friends, and campus scenes.
      - Scrapbook, 1899-1900 (Box 31, Folder 4)
        Describes Willard Straight's activities during his junior year at Cornell.
  - Series III Far East
    - Professional
      - Notebook, 1905 (Box 31, Folder 6)
        Russo-Japanese War, includes notes on Japanese and Russian military strength and Straight's wardrope list.
      - Documents on Far Eastern Currency--transcripts. (Box 19, Folder 16-17)
      - Notes--includes a sketch by Ellen B. Straight (Box 19, Folder 18)
      - Clippings--describe events during the Russo-Japanese War., 1902-1906 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      - Clippings--describe unrest in China., 1908-1911 (Box 20, Folder 2)
      - Clippings, 1912 (Box 20, Folder 3)
        Describe rebellion in early 1912 during which the Straight's home in Peking was ransacked.
      - The Toronto Sunday World, Oct. 13, 1912, article "How I escaped the Chinese bandits", 1912 (Folder 1)
        Describes Dorothy Whitney's escape from looters at the Pierpont Morgan compound in Peking during a recent uprising.
      - Clippings, n.d., 1902-1912 (Box 20, Folder 4)
        Describe Far Eastern events from 1902-1912 with letters describing clipping services from which many of the clippings came.
      - Duplicate Correspondence--carbon copies., 1907-1910 (Box 32, Folder 2)
      - Duplicate Correspondence--one bound volume, carbon copies., 1908-1912 (Box 33, Folder 2)
      - Clippings--one bound volume, Russo-Japanese War, 1904-1905 (Box 33, Folder 1)
      - Clippings--one bound volume, Japan in Korea, c., 1905 (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Clippings, 1905 (Box 34, Folder 2)
        One bound volume, Russo-Japanese War; Battle of Heikoutai to Anti-Peace Demonstrations in Tokyo, February-September 1905.
      - Notebook-Miscellaneous notes, n.d. (Box 20, Folder 5)
      - Pamphlets (Box 20, Folder 6)
        "Polo in China," "Edward Henry Harriman," "Personal Impressions of Edward Henry Harriman," "The Heathen Invasion" by Claude Bragdon, Russian railroad timetable.
      - Pamphlets, 1911 (Box 20, Folder 7)
        "Diary of the Revolution," reprints from the Hankow Daily News from Oct. 10-Nov.28, 1911, 2 volumes.
    - Personal
      - Letters--to Gertrude D. Cox, 1902-1904., 1902-1904 (Box 85)
        Written from China, Japan, and Korea, including sketches on the letters; three photographs; and a postcard.
      - Guestbook, 1907-1908., 1907-1908 (Box 30, Folder 4)
      - Check Stubs, 1906-1907 (Box 20, Folder 8)
      - Check Stubs--includes financial accounts., 1907, 1912 (Box 20, Folder 9)
      - Checks and Stubs., 1908, 1911 (Box 20, Folder 10)
      - Financial records, 1912 (Box 20, Folder 11)
        Includes checks and check stubs, 1912, n.d.
      - Financial records, 1907-1912 (Box 20, Folder 12)
        Includes receipts from 1907-1912, checks, and two items in Chinese.
      - Greeting Cards and Calling Cards--from China., 1911 (Box 20, Folder 13)
      - Japanese theatre program, temporary passport., 1911 (Box 20, Folder 14)
      - Clippings--describe Straight's wedding., 1911 (Box 20, Folder 15)
      - Chinese Manuscripts, 1980 (Box 35)
        Described by Diane Perushek, Curator of the Wason Collection, Olin Library, 1980.
      - Japanese and Korean Manuscripts, 1904-1905 (Box 35, Folder 1)
        Reuters byline, interview referring to military and railroads, 1904-1905
      - Chinese Manuscripts (Box 35, Folder 2)
        Depiction of battle, revolutionary poster, prints of Buddhist Pantheons.
      - Korean Poster, 1907 (Box 35, Folder 3)
        Protest against paying Chinese taxes, 1907.
      - Pamphlet--on Korea in Japanese., 1905 (Box 35, Folder 4)
      - Manchu Manuscripts--possibly a zodiac calender. (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - Chinese Correspondence (Box 35, Folder 6)
        Invitation, manuscript about railroad contract, calling cards, notes, receipt.
      - Chinese Correspondence (Box 35, Folder 7)
        Personal, includes various envelopes and Straight's calling cards.
      - Newspaper clippings--Chinese, 1912., 1912 (Box 35, Folder 8)
      - Financial records, 1906, 1907 (Box 35, Folder 9)
      - Pamphlets--Chinese (Box 35, Folder 10)
      - Memorandum--concerning Korean-Manchurian border, 1877., 1877 (Box 35, Folder 11)
  - Series IV U.S.A.
    - The New Republic
      - The New Republic, 1914 (Box 20, Folder 16)
        Speech by Herbert Croly announcing plan to publish The New Republic
      - The New Republic--pamphlet. (Box 20, Folder 17)
        "The New Republic Idea" by Herbert Croly, program from banquet celebrating first anniversary of founding of the magazine.
    - Personal and Career
      - Address book and 1914 diary, 1914 (Box 31, Folder 8)
        Diary contains miscellaneous notes.
      - Clippings, 1914, 1915 (Box 20, Folder 18)
      - Clippings, 1916, 1917 (Box 20, Folder 19)
      - Financial records--receipts, 1912, 1914, 1917 (Box 20, Folder 20)
      - Program, 1913 (Box 20, Folder 21)
        For dinner of Cornell Architects in New York.
      - Italian Manuscript (Box 20, Folder 22)
        Collected by Willard Straight, probably a review of a work by Jean Francois Fouquet in 1729.
      - 1130 Fifth Avenue (Box 21, Folder 1)
        Exterior and interior photographs of Willard and Dorothy Straight's home, including an article in Harper's Bazaar on the house.
      - Calling cards, place cards, sketches. (Box 21, Folder 2)
      - Invitations, safe-conduct pass, floor plan sketches. (Box 21, Folder 3)
      - List of friends. (Box 21, Folder 4)
      - Straight children (Box 21, Folder 5)
        Clippings describe activities of Whitney, Michael, and Beatrice Straight after their father's death.
      - Mayor's Committee on National Defense, 1917 (Box 30, Folder 1)
        Resolution of support for President and war effort.
      - Music composed by Willard Straight--annotated by Dorothy Straight. (Box 34, Folder 3)
      - Scrapbooks--include architectural photographs. (Box 37-38)
  - Series V Military Training and Service
    - Military Training
      - Oversize photographs (Box 91)
        Book from Camp of Instruction, August 10-September 6, 1915.
        Includes photographs of classmates, military training, the White House, President Roosevelt and Woodrow Wilson
      - Plattsburg (Box 30, Folder 2)
      - Notebook (Box 30, Folder 3)
        General orders, Governor's Island, New York; Ft. Sill, Oklahoma.
      - Notebooks, 1917-1918 (Box 31, Folder 10)
        Notes, manuals, orders, and references to books, from France, 1917-1918.
      - Notebooks, 1916-1918 (Box 21, Folder 6)
        Contain diary entries and notes on military training.
      - Notebook (Box 21, Folder 7)
        War Risk Insurance Bureau.
      - Notebook, 1917-1918 (Box 21, Folder 8)
        Orders, Distinguished Service Award notice, War Department correspondence, 1917-1918.
      - Notebook (Box 21, Folder 9)
        Duplicates of military correspondence.
      - Pamphlets (Box 22, Folder 1)
        Explanation of War Risk Insurance, Army pay tables.
      - Pamphlets (Box 22, Folder 2)
        Awards of Distinguished Service Medal, Intelligence regulations.
      - War Documents (Box 22, Folder 3)
        Receipts, vouchers, personnel lists for War Risk Insurance Bureau.
      - American Expeditionary Forces, 1919 (Box 22, Folder 4)
        Notes prepared by Brigadier General Fox Conner, Chief G-3, G.H.Q., 1919.
      - Forms, orders--instruction for filing reports. (Box 22, Folder 5)
      - War Risk Insurance (Box 22, Folder 6)
        Correspondence, reports on War Risk Insurance
      - Langres (Box 22, Folder 7)
        Photos and text describing rectories and monasteries in Langres.
      - Notes--from Army Staff College at Langres. (Box 22, Folder 8-9)
      - Army General Staff College, 1918 (Box 22, Folder 10)
        Pamphlets with roster, cartoons, and songs from second course, 1918.
      - Personal receipts and clippings, 1918 (Box 22, Folder 11)
        Describe war service, includes nameplate for printing calling cards.
      - Typed transcriptions of letters of condolence on Straight's death. (Box 36, Folder 1-5)
      - List of correspondence. (Box 36, Folder 9)
    - Death/Suresnes
      - Mounted clippings (Box 22, Folder 12)
        Describe Straight's death and will.
      - Clippings (Box 22, Folder 13)
      - Scrapbook (Box 28, Folder 2)
        Contains clippings on Straight's death.
      - Illness (Box 23, Folder 1)
        Nurse's charts, telephone inquiries, and notes received during Straight's illness and upon his death.
      - Calling cards--received during Straight's illness. (Box 23, Folder 2)
      - Calling cards and flower cards--received at time of Straight's death. (Box 23, Folder 3-10)
      - Calling cards--used by Dorothy Straight (Box 23, Folder 11)
      - Ribbon (Box 23, Folder 12)
        From Marshall Foch, probably from floral arrangement at funeral.
      - Ribbon (Box 23, Folder 13)
        From J.P. Morgan and Co.
      - Plaques (Box 23, Folder 14)
        From Straight's grave, includes an explanatory letter.
      - American Cemetery, Suresnes--photographs (Box 22, Folder 14)
      - Pamphlets (Box 22, Folder 15)
        On war dead and military burials in France.
      - Pamphlets (Box 22, Folder 16)
        On Memorial Day in France and on American soldiers buried in France.
      - Cemetery beautification, Suresnes (Box 22, Folder 17)
        Photographs of Jo Davidson and "The Doughboy," with sketches and clippings describing cemetery beautification.
      - Cemetery beautification, Suresnes, annotated in French (Box 22, Folder 18)
        Photographs of Suresnes cemetery, "The Doughboy" dedication, models of Suresnes cemetery, and transplanting trees.
      - Suresnes (Box 22, Folder 19)
        Sketches and plans for monument and cemetery grounds at Suresnes.
      - Financial Records (Box 24, Folder 1)
        Detailing cost of cemetery beautification, mostly in French.
  - Series VI Events After Willard Straight's Death
    - Tributes
      - Transcripts (Box 24, Folder 2)
        Of various tributes, includes original correspondence from Manton M. Wyvill ('01) and lists of organizations who adopted resolutions of sympathy.
      - Frank E. Bolway & Sons, Inc; Oswego Yarn Mills, Inc.--tributes. (Box 24, Folder 3)
      - Board of Directors of Asia magazine (Box 24, Folder 4)
        Resolution of sympathy
      - Board of Governors of India House (Box 24, Folder 5)
        Tribute and resolution of sympathy
      - American International Corporation (Box 24, Folder 6)
        Tribute
      - United States Army, The New Republic--tribute (Box 30, Folder 7)
      - Lists (Box 24, Folder 7)
        People who attended Straight's funeral, sent condolence, received a copy of Straight's biography.
      - Clippings, 1919-1924 (Box 24, Folder 8)
        Include mention of Straight and former associates.
      - Bound clippings (Box 29)
        Detail events throughout Straight's life.
      - Willard Straight Agricultural School (Box 29, Folder 1)
        Photograph and newsletter from school in Indanan, Sulu, Philippine Islands.
    - Publications and Drafts
      - Scribners (Box 24, Folder 9)
        June 1919 issue includes a series of letters from Straight to Claude Bragdon.
      - Memoirs (Box 24, Folder 10)
        By Edwin V. Morgan, Maurice Casenave, and Dorothy W. Straight, compiled for Straight's biography and articles in Asia magazine.
      - Correspondence (Box 24, Folder 11)
        Notes in preparation for Asia articles and biography.
      - Asia (Box 24, Folder 12)
        Copies of Straight's correspondence, excerpted for articles, annotated, incomplete; November 5, 1910 - February 12, 1911; February 17, 1911 - May 20, 1911.
      - Correspondence (Box 24, Folder 13)
        A-C in preparation for Asia articles and biography.
      - Correspondence (Box 24, Folder 14)
        D-G in prepartion for Asia articles and biography.
      - Correspondence (Box 25, Folder 1)
        H-M in preparation for Asia articles and biography.
      - Correspondence (Box 25, Folder 2)
        N-R in preparation for Asia articles and biography.
      - Correspondence (Box 25, Folder 3)
        S-W in preparation for Asia articles and biography.
      - Notes (Box 25, Folder 4)
        For Asia article, includes copy of advertisement for The New Republic announcing the series.
      - "An American in Asia" (Box 25, Folder 5)
        Drafts of article series for Asia magazine.
      - "An American in Asia" (Box 25, Folder 6)
        Rough drafts of chapter three, proofs of chapter one, and proofs of Willard Straight in the Orient, based on these articles.
      - Broadside, 1922 (Box 36, Folder 10)
        Advertisement of Asia magazine issue on Near East, April 1922
      - Willard Straight in the Orient--by Louis Graves (Box 31, Folder 2)
      - Notes (Box 25, Folder 7)
        For preparation of biography.
      - Notebook (Box 25, Folder 8)
        Notes on biography, list of people who sent letters to the Straights, lists of Straight's sketches.
      - Notes (Box 25, Folder 9)